07 - Future Tasks of the Alliance - “Harmel Report”
NATO Archives Online
07 - Future Tasks of the Alliance - “Harmel Report”
1966-12-13
HARMEL
385 Items
NATO Archives Online Boulevard Léopold III NATO Headquarters Brussels Capital Belgium 1110 Email: nato.archives@hq.nato.int https://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/68238.htm
Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance
In late 1966, the approaching 20th anniversary of NATO and the adjustments made necessary by the French decision of 1966 to withdraw from the military integrated structure prompted the Alliance to re-examine its relevance and adaptation to the existing political context.
At the December 1966 NATO Meeting of Foreign Ministers, Pierre Harmel, Belgium’s Foreign Minister, tabled a proposal calling for a joint analysis of the major events of the past twenty years. He recommended the study be used to determine the effect of events on the objectives and methods of the Alliance and decide whether it was necessary to improve consultation within it. The Foreign Affairs Ministers responded favourably to Harmel’s proposal and empowered Manlio Brosio, NATO Secretary General and the Permanent Representatives to the North Atlantic Council (NAC) with a comprehensive mandate to develop procedures for the study and determine its scope.
In February 1967, the NAC decided to constitute an open-ended Special Group of representatives designated by governments, under the Chairmanship of the Secretary General. The NAC gave the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance (also known under the reference AC/261) the task of studying “ (a) the development of political events as it affects the purposes of the Alliance; (b) the consequent future tasks of the Alliance”. The Special Group was to establish such special procedures, sub-groups and rapporteurs, and request such staff work from the International Staff as it deemed necessary” [ see reference C-M(67)11].
During the month of March 1967 the Special Group met on five occasions in private session to encourage wide ranging discussions. It was during these meetings that they decided on the framework for the conduct of the study. The Special Group created four sub-groups were created, each working on a broad subject of interest to the Alliance and under the guidance of a rapporteur of repute:
• Sub-Group One, East/West Relations: Mr. K.Schutz, State Secretary, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Germany and Mr. J.H.A. Watson, Assistant Under Secretary of State. Foreign Affairs, United Kingdom
• Sub-Group Two, Inter-allied Relations: Mr. Paul-Henri Spaak, Minister of State, Belgium
• Sub-Group Three, General Defence Policy: Mr. Foy Kohler, Deputy Under Secretary of State, United States
• Sub-Group Four, Relations with other Countries: Dr. C.L. Patijn, Professor of International Relations, University of Utrecht (Netherlands)
The NATO International Staff provided secretarial support and was tasked with gathering background material for the sub-groups.
The sub-groups met several times from May to June to prepare a draft interim report which was approved by the NAC [se reference C-M(67)33] following some amendments at their Ministerial meeting of 13 - 14 June in Luxembourg.
Following this initial phase, the sub-groups began to address the substantive issues. Although the reports were prepared under the responsibility of each rapporteur, a meeting of all the sub-groups took place in July to harmonise the work and avoid duplication. After having gone through several stages, the reports were reviewed and their findings compared during a last meeting in October at Ditchley Park (UK).
The following month, the Special Group held a high-level meeting over two days during which the substance of the Report was discussed. The Secretary General circulated a draft Report which was discussed and amended by the Special Group on 22 November 1967.
The Report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance was presented at the NATO Ministerial Session and after some last amendments was approved by Foreign Affairs Ministers on 14 December 1967 and subsequently released to the press [See reference C-M(67)74(2nd revised) and M4(67)3, respectively].
published
HARMEL
NAO
This series of files consists of the records created or received by the NATO International Staff and related to the study on the Future Tasks of the Alliance between December 1966 and December 1967. It includes formal and informal documents of the Special Group and of its four Sub-groups as well as documents from the Council, the Secretary General, summary records of private meetings of Permanent Representatives, internal notes and national contributions.
It should be noted that the meetings of the Special Group and of its sub-groups were held in private session. No official minutes of the meetings were issued under reference AC/261.
The documents are arranged chronologically. Most of the formal documents exist both in English and in French. The informal documents and national contributions exist in the language in which they were drafted.
The ten file volumes in this series are not organic and they have been assembled by the International Staff Archives from files initially created by the Political Affairs, Defence Planning and Policy Sub-registries of the International Staff and the Private Office of the Secretary General.
NATO publicly disclosed information is available for research and education purposes. Any commercial use requires the written permission of NATO. Please credit the NATO Archives should any documents be used for publication. Guidelines for the proper citation of NATO publicly disclosed information can be found on the NATO Archives website (http://www.nato.int/archives).
- Proposal of Study by P. Harmel and initial considerations (December 1966 – February 1967), 1966-12 - 1967-02; Volume 1; 40 Items
  published
  NATO publicly disclosed information is available for research and education purposes. Any commercial use requires the written permission of NATO. Please credit the NATO Archives should any documents be used for publication. Guidelines for the proper citation of NATO publicly disclosed information can be found on the NATO Archives website (http://www.nato.int/archives).
  - Proposal by Pierre Harmel, Belgian Minister of Foreign Affairs for a broad analysis of international developments since the signing of the Treaty and establishment by the Council of a Special Group tasked with studying the future tasks of the Alliance, Section 1
    - Private letter from Ambassador de Staercke to Secretary General asking that Mr. Harmel’s proposals for a cohesive analysis of all major political events and their effects on the Alliance be given due consideration at the next NATO Council meeting, 1966-12-13; 2390.D.41.8; 2 pages
    - NATO Council meeting on 15 December 1966. Extract on the reasons for Mr. Harmel’s proposal being accepted. (27 January 1967) BIL, 1967-01-27; C-R(66)68 and 69; 6 pages
    - Ministerial sessions. Draft resolution on the decision by the North Atlantic Council about the elaboration of a report on future tasks of the Alliance. (15 December 1966) FRE 1, 1966-12-15; Projet; 1 page
    - Political Affairs, Special Question Section. Declaration by Italian Foreign Minister Fanfani on Mr. Harmel’s resolution. (15 December 1966) FRE 1, 1966-12-15; SQS/66/165; 1 page
    - NATO Council meeting on the 16 December 1966. Extract on the Council’s adoption of Harmel’s resolution. (30 January 1967) BIL 1, 1966-12-16; C-R(66)71 Extract; 2 pages
    - Declaration to the press of the Council’s acceptance of Harmel’s proposals. (16 December 1966) BIL 1, 1966-12-16; Press Release M3(66)3; 4 pages
    - NATO Council memorandum on Harmel’s proposals and its acceptance by the Council. (27 December 1966) BIL 1, 1966-12-27; C-M(66)145; 2 pages
  - Initial considerations on the substance of the study to be carried out and the procedure to be followed, Section 2
    - Memorandum from K. Inan to the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs on the preliminary reflections on the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (28 December 1966) FRE 1, 1966-12-28; Memo; 8 pages
    - Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Note from A. Alacakaptan to Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs on the future tasks of the Alliance. (3 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-03; GAS/67/7; 2 pages
    - Political Affairs Division Research Section. Memorandum from A.G. Kühn to ASG Political Affairs on a list of suggestions for action regarding the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (6 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-06; RS/67/2; 2 pages
    - Political Affairs Division Research Section. Memorandum from A.G. Kuhn to the ASG Political Affairs discussing the means in which the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance may be carried out and possible outcomes thereof. (9 January 1967, 1967-01-09; RS/67/4; 3 pages
    - NATO Council meeting on 11 January 1967. Extracts on the preliminary discussions regarding the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (19 January 1967) BIL 1, 1967-01-11; C-R(67)1 Extract; 4 pages
    - Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Note from ASG Political Affairs to the Secretary General on preliminary efforts to define the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (13 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-13; GAS/67/5; 5 pages
    - Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Memorandum from Christian Chapman to the Secretary General on his preliminary thoughts on the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (13 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-13; GAS/67/6; 3 pages
    - Minutes from a meeting of the Secretary General and selected members of the International Staff concerning the Belgian government’s initial ideas for the procedures relating to the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (16 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-16; Note; 5 pages
    - Minutes on a meeting between the Secretary General and selected members of the International Staff on further procedures relating to the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (20 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-20; Note; 6 pages
    - Mr. Baccetti, director of Private Office. Contribution on the resolution on future tasks of the Alliance. (17 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-17; Private Office Memo; 4 pages
    - Political Affairs Division Research Section. Memorandum from W.M. Newton to the ASG Political Affairs on reasons and circumstances leading to the signature of the North Atlantic Treaty. (19 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-19; RS/67/12; 5 pages
    - Political Affairs Division, Special Questions Section. Memorandum from the Assistant Secretary General to the Secretary General on the prevalent situation in Europe and Asia in 1948 and how it led to the creation of NATO. (31 January 1967) FRE, 1967-01-31; DPA/SQS/67; 8 pages
    - Memorandum from Mr. Inan to ASG Political Affairs. Collection of publications with proposals on the re-organization of NATO from 1963 to 1997. (13 February 1967) FRE 1, 1967-02-13; Memo; 17 pages
  - Submission by the Secretary General of a tentative outline on the substance and procedures for the study, Section 3
    - Draft memorandum from Mr. van Campen, special advisor for policy planning, to Secretary General on the principal elements, up to that date, of talks on the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (31 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-01-31; Political Affairs Division Memo; 7 pages
    - Second draft of Memorandum from Mr. van Campen, special advisor for policy planning, to Secretary General on the principal elements, up to that date, of talks on the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (8 February 1967) ENG, 1967-02-08; Political Affairs Division Memo; 8 pages
    - Final draft of Memorandum from Mr. van Campen, special advisor for policy planning, to Secretary General on the principal elements, up to that date, of talks on the resolution on the future tasks of NATO. (9 February 1967) ENG, 1967-02-09; Political Affairs Division Draft Memo; 7 pages
    - Private Office. Preliminary suggestions on the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (10 February 1967) BIL 1, 1967-02-10; PO(67)89; 10 pages
  - A call for member countries to attend the first round of Council discussions on the resolution of the future tasks of the Alliance, Section 4
    - Private Office. Memo from Secretary General asking member countries for attendance at the next Council meeting on 15 February where Mr. Harmel would participate. (27 January 1967) BIL 1, 1967-01-27; PO(67)54; 2 pages
  - Responses to the Secretary General’s attendance query regarding the first round of talks on the future tasks of the Alliance, Section 5
    - Memorandum from Mr. Harmel, Belgian Minister of Foreign Affairs, confirming his planned attendance at the following Council meeting and outlining his ideas for the future tasks of NATO. (25 January 1967) FRE 1, 1967-01-25; Memo; 3 pages
    - Memorandum confirming the attendance of Under Secretary Eugene Rostow at the Council meeting discussing the future tasks of the Alliance. (2 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-02; United States Delegation Letter; 1 page
    - Memorandum from Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs F. Jacobsen confirming his presence at the Council meeting on the future tasks of the Alliance. (9 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-09; Norwegian Delegation Letter; 1 page
    - Memo by Permanent Representative Bernard Burrows to the Secretary General putting forth his ideas for the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (10 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-10; United Kingdom Delegation Letter; 3 pages
  - The first Council meeting on the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance, Section 6
    - First draft, opening statement by the Secretary General at the first Council meeting on the future tasks of the Alliance. (13 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-13; Speaking Notes; 3 pages
    - Remarks by Mr. George Thompson, British Representative, to the North Atlantic Council. (15 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-15; Speaking Notes; 3 pages
    - Introduction by Mr. Harmel, Belgian Minister of Foreign Affairs, highlighting his plans for the implementation of the Council’s resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (15 February 1967) FRE 1, 1967-02-15; Speaking Notes; 7 pages
    - Statement by K. Schütz, State Secretary German Foreign Office, on his impressions of the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (15 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-15; Speaking Notes; 5 pages
    - Council Verbatim Record of Council Meeting on 15 February 1967 containing discussion on the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance. (15 February 1967) ENG+FRE 1, 1967-02-15; C-VR(67)8; 47 pages
    - Executive Secretariat. Memorandum from R. D. Coleridge, Executive Secretary, discussing the creation of a Special Group to carry out the mandate of the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance (16 February 1967) FRE 1, 1967-02-16; RDC/67/55; 2 pages
  - Decisions on procedure for the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance, Section 7
    - Political Affairs Division. Memorandum from ASG Political Affairs to the Secretary General containing an abstract of issues discussed during the Council meeting on 15 February 1967. (21 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-21; DPA/67/45; 5 pages
    - Political Affairs Division. Memorandum from ASG Political Affairs to the Secretary General discussing options on how the resolution may be received by the Council. (21 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-21; DPA/67/47; 2 pages
    - Political Affairs Division. Memorandum from the ASG Political Affairs to the Secretary General on the forthcoming Council discussions on the resolution on the future tasks of the Alliance and the outcomes thereof. (21 January 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-21; DPA/67/…; 3 pages
    - NATO Council meeting on the 22 February 1967. Decisions on procedure about the future tasks of the Alliance. (1 March 1967) BIL 1, 1967-03-01; C-R(67)9 Extract; 4 pages
    - Council memorandum outlining decisions made on the procedure on future tasks of the Alliance: creation of a Special Group to report on the future tasks of the Alliance (24 February 1967) BIL 1, 1967-02-24; C-M(67)11; 2 pages
- Purposes and procedure of the Study: composition of the four sub-groups (February 1967 – May 1967), 1967-02 - 1967-05; Volume 2; 62 Items
  - Designation of Country representatives for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 1
    - Private Office. Note by Secretary General Manlio Brosio to Permanent Representatives requesting the names of those attending the Special Group on Future Tasks of the Alliance. (27 February 1967) BIL 1, 1967-02-27; PO/67/132; 2 pages
    - Icelandic Delegation. Letter from H. Björnsson, Permanent Representative Icelandic Delegation, to the Secretary General replying to his query in PO/67/132 (28 February 1967) ENG 1, 1967-02-28; 9.N.5; 1 page
    - Letter from A. Alessandrini, Italian Permanent Representative, to Secretary General replying to his query in PO/67/132. (1 march 1967) FRE 1, 1967-03-01; Italian Delegation Letter; 1 page
    - Letter from B. Burrows, British Permanent Representative to Secretary General replying to his query in PO/67/132 (2 march 1967) ENG 1, 1967-03-02; United Kingdom Delegation Letter; 1 page
    - Letter from R. Busch, Permanent Representative, to Secretary General replying to his query in PO/67/132 (3 March 1967) ENG 1, 1967-03-03; Norwegian Delegation Letter; 1 page
    - Memorandum from F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary, listing those attending the Special Group. (3 March 1967) ENG 1, 1967-03-03; FCM/67/47; 1 page
  - Meetings in the Secretary General’s office to examine the aim, purpose and procedures of the study, Section 2
    - Draft record of the meeting in Secretary General’s office on the issues and workload distribution regarding the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (25 February 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of a meeting in the Secretary General’s office on the aims and purpose of the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (27 February 1967) ENG 1
  - Summary of the Council’s decision on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 3
    - PO/67/133. Private Office. Memorandum by the Secretary General to the Permanent Representatives, summarizing the topics proposed for the analysis, tasks and conclusions stages during the previous Council meeting on 15 February. (27 February 1967) BIL 1
  - The first round of Special Group meetings leading to the creation of four Sub-groups, Section 4
    - AC/261-A/1. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Circulation of the draft agenda for the first meeting of the Special Group. (23 February 1967) ENG 1
    - Terms of reference for the Special Working Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (1 March 1967) ENG 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Initial ideas on work load distribution on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (4 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft of the Secretary General’s speech for the first meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance on 6 March 1967. (2 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Text of the opening speech of the Secretary General at the meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance on 6 March 1967. (4 March 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-WP(67)1. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note containing a declaration by the Secretary General during the first meeting of the group regarding preparation for the next meeting (9 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Memorandum by F. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary, to the Secretary General on summary meeting of the Special Group held on 6 March 1967 and Belgian, British and American proposals. (10 march 1967) ENG + FRE 1
    - United States Delegation. Letter from the Secretary of the US Delegation, Mr. T. Johnson, to the Executive Secretary and Delegations with attached list of suggested items for study, put forward by the Secretary General during his last intervention. (6 Mar
    - Belgian Delegation. Questions to study for the first meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (6 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Italian Delegation. Questions to be considered by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (8 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft working paper from ASG Political affairs for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (8 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Working paper from the ASG political Affairs containing the next draft of the working program on the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (10 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft working paper from the Secretary General on the working program for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (13 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Decision sheet Regarding working program and summary of delegations proposals after the meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance that met 13 March 1967. (18 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Belgian Delegation. Working paper with suggestions and ideas for the work program of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (March 1967) FRE 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General outlining a list of subjects for the sub-groups of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (14 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft working program from the Secretary General with his contribution to the discussions and decisions of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (14 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Revised working paper from the Secretary General with his contribution to the discussions and decisions of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (14 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Revised working paper from the Secretary General with his contribution to the discussions and decisions of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (14 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Memorandum from F. Menne to the Secretary General with summary record of the meeting of the Special Group held 17 March 1967, discussing the representative’s ideas on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (20 March 1967) ENG 1
    - 2nd Revised working paper from Secretary General detailing his ideas for the work program for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (20 March 1967) FRE 1
    - 2nd Revised working paper from Secretary General detailing his ideas for the work program for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (20 March 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-N/1..Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note informing of a change in the date and time of the next meeting. (20 March 1967) BIL 1
    - Brief on the chairman’s speech to the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (March 1967) ENG 1
    - Memorandum from F. Menne to the Secretary General with summary record of the meeting on the 22 March discussing the countries queries on the work program. (23 March 1967) FRE 1
    - Minutes of a private meeting of Permanent Representatives, chaired by the Deputy Secretary General. (23 March 1967) ENG 1
    - Memorandum from F. Menne to the Secretary General with a summary record of the Special Group private meeting on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, on the organization of the studies involved. (29 March 1967) ENG 1
  - Composition of the Sub-groups on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 5
    - AC/261-N/2..Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note informing delegations of the times at which the first meetings of the four sub-groups will be held. (31 March 1967) BIL 1
    - Belgian Delegation. Letter confirming the presence of Mr. Spaak as the representative for Belgium in sub-group 2 Inter-Allied Relations. (4 April 1967) FRE 1
    - DPA/67/91. Political Affairs Division. Memorandum from ASG Political Affairs to the Secretary General on the present status and organization of sub-groups and participants (10 April 1967) ENG 1